Finding Aid for Edson Read Sunderland Papers 1892-1959
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edson Read Sunderland Papers 1892-1959, 1923-1953
Sunderland, Edson R. (Edson Read), b. 1874.
18.5 linear feet
Legal scholar and professor of law and legal research at the University of Michigan, 1901 to 1944. Papers include biographical material, speeches and articles, and files related to teaching, research and involvement in professional organizations.
85398 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Alice Sunderland Wethy (donor no. 3061) in 1972 and 1993, with a major addition donated by David Sunderland Wethy (donor no. 10888) in 2013. A few items were donated Mrs. Janet Toohy Ferguson (donor no. 9192 ) in 2002.
The collection is open for research.
Edson Read Sunderland was born in 1874 in Northfield, Massachusetts, but spent most of his childhood in Ann Arbor, Michigan. His father, the Reverend Jabez Sunderland, was pastor of the First Unitarian Church in Ann Arbor from 1878 to 1898 and an internationally known religious leader. His mother, Dr. Eliza R. Sunderland, was a distinguished educator, author, and advocate of women's rights. Edson Sunderland attended the University of Berlin and the University of California and earned three degrees from the University of Michigan -- a bachelor of arts in 1897, a master of arts in philosophy in 1898, and a bachelor of law in 1901. Immediately upon receiving his LL.B. degree from Michigan, he accepted an invitation to join the faculty, embarking upon a career of teaching, research and writing for which he would become nationally recognized.
Sunderland served as a secretary of the state bar association and editor of the state bar journal from 1922 to 1924, becoming an active advocate for reform in legal procedure. In 1927, the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan designated Sunderland the first holder of a professorship in legal research. In the same year, he was appointed by the Michigan legislature, along with four other Michigan attorneys, to a state commission whose mandate was to confer with the Justices of the Michigan Supreme Court and suggest revised rules of practice and procedure, including a simplified method of appellate procedure. Sunderland devoted a large portion of his time in the next two years to the work of preparing the new rules, distributing a preliminary report published by the Legal Research Institute of the university in 1928 and a final report in 1929. In 1930, the rules were published by the Institute in their final form as adopted by the Supreme Court and offered to the bar of Michigan at printer's cost in accordance with the wishes of William W. Cook, donor of the legal research endowment funds.
A prolific writer, Sunderland authored more than twenty book-length publications and more than 130 articles on legal problems. His series of casebooks, published beginning in 1912 covering trial practice, code pleading, common law pleading and finally in 1924, trial and appellate practice, were pioneering for the teaching of procedure. He spoke and wrote regularly about the weak points of the procedural system, constantly pointing out the need for reform. In an article entitled, "The Inefficiency of the American Jury," published in 1915, he urged that judges not only be permitted, but be required, to aid juries in reaching just conclusions on matters of fact, observing that no single reform would do more to promote the efficiency of courts and the quality of justice. In 1917, he called attention to the then well-established English practice of giving declaratory judgments before trial, referring to it as a modern evolution in remedial rights -- "an advance over previous doctrines comparable to the great reform which equity made over the harsh rules of the common law." This article, one of the first in the country to urge the adoption of the practice, was followed by at least eight others in which he explained the practice and called for its adoption.
In 1932, Sunderland wrote in the foreword to a study on discovery published by one of his graduate students that, "It is probable that no procedural process offers greater opportunities for increasing the efficiency of the administration of justice than that of discovery before trial." His continued interest in discovery is evidenced in the publication of at least seven articles on the subject, along with his work for the United States Supreme Court Advisory Committee which formulated the Federal Rules of 1938. His contribution to the work of the Committee also included provision for summary judgments -- a procedure which had received his special attention when drafting the Michigan Court rules of 1931. In 1937, he called attention to pre-trial procedures that had been developed in Detroit, remarking that pre-trial conferences (including judge, prosecutor and defense attorney) provided "an open, business-like and efficient presentation of real issues," and "that its general adoption and use might do much to restore the confidence of the public in litigation as a desirable means of settling disputes."
In the field of appellate practice Sunderland urged, among other reforms, the simplification of the appellate record, and he expressed strong opposition to double appeals made necessary by systems of intermediate appellate courts. In this area he wrote some eighteen articles. Sunderland's writings were voluminous, and he was in constant demand as a speaker at bar association meetings. In almost all cases, his speeches resulted in published papers. His last book, The History of the American Bar Association, was written long after his retirement and published in 1953 by the association for distribution among its members. On his 84th birthday in 1958, his family presented him with, and distributed, a privately printed bibliography of his writings.
Nationally recognized for his scholarship, Sunderland was a research associate with the Sterling Foundation at Yale University from 1921 to 1922, a visiting professor at the University of Chicago in 1934, the University of North Carolina from 1935 to1938, and the University of Southern California in 1936. He was president of the Association of American Law Schools in 1930, chairman of the National Conference of Judicial Councils in 1932, and a director of the American Judicature Society. In 1933 he drafted the Illinois Civil Practices Act, which was adopted in that same year.
In addition to his Law School work, Sunderland served for twenty-five years as business manager of the Faculty Board in Control of Student Publications. The organization was bankrupt when he took over in 1917, but he turned it around with both financial and editorial advice. By 1931, Sunderland had accumulated enough reserves to initiate plans for a new building designed by Irving K. Pond, equipping it with the best and latest printing presses. Also active in area community affairs, he served from 1925 to 1934 on the Ann Arbor Board of Education and from 1931 to 1943 as a director of Cranbrook's Kingswood School, Bloomfield Hills, Michigan. Sunderland was married to Hannah Dell Read and had a son and two daughters.
In 1952 Professor Sunderland received an honorary doctor of laws degree from the University of Michigan, an honor seldom bestowed upon one its own faculty members. He also received honorary degrees from Wayne State University and Northwestern University. When he died in 1959 at age eighty-five, the Michigan Law Review dedicated its November issue to his memory.
The papers are organized into eight series including
Biographical Materials (0.75 linear feet)
Research Material and Reports (7.25 linear feet)
Organizations and Committees (2 linear feet)
Correspondence (4 linear feet)
Law School, University of Michigan (1 linear foot)
Faculty Board in Control of Student Publications (0.5 linear feet)
Speeches and Articles (3 linear feet)
The Edson Read Sunderland collection (18.5 linear feet) spans the years 1892-1959 with the bulk of the material covering 1923-1953. Sunderland's steady and vigorous advocacy for reform in legal procedures, including the drafting of procedures for the courts of the United States, Michigan, and Illinois are well documented in the papers. When considered as a whole, the collection (which is comprised mainly of writings, speeches, research materials, and correspondence) reflects Sunderland's meticulous and focused approach to legal scholarship.
The papers are organized into eight series including Biographical Materials (0.75 linear feet), Research Material and Reports (7.25 linear ft.), Organizations and Committees (2.0 linear feet), Correspondence (4 linear feet), Law School, University of Michigan (1 linear foot), Faculty Board in Control of Student Publications (0.5 linear feet), and Speeches and Articles (3 linear feet).
Subjects:
Legal research.; Law.; Legal reform.; Sunderland, Edson R. (Edson Read), b. 1874.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.
- Biographical Materials
  Since most of the series are mainly evidential to Sunderland's professional life, researchers interested in a broader perspective will find the Biographical Materials of interest, although the documentation is limited a handful of newspaper clippings and photographs, several volumes of travel journals, and papers written in his youth. The series also includes seven folders of personal correspondence -- mainly letters from family and friends while Sunderland was a student at the University of Michigan. A more complete view of the Sunderland family as a whole can be found in the collection of Sunderland-Safford family papers. This collection, which includes the papers of Edson Sunderland's sister, Gertrude Sunderland Safford, includes extensive family correspondence. In addition, researchers should note that there is extensive background information in Alice Sunderland Wethy's A Genealogical-Biographical Compilation of the Sunderland and Broadhead Families (Bentley Historical Library call number DB/2/S958/W539/v.2).
  - Clippings 1905-1936 (Box 1)
  - Condolences: Deaths of Eliza and Jabez Sunderland 1910, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (largely with family members)
    - 1895-1900, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1900, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1909-1920 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (mainly portraits; includes Ann Arbor High School Physics Lab, ca. 1892) (Box 1)
  - Student Papers and Notes 1896 (Box 1)
  - Travel Journals 1895-1896, 1898-1899 (Box 1)
  - Writings (Youth) undated (Box 1)
  - Tributes by Michigan Law Faculty and Bibliography of Legal Writings 1959 (Box 1)
- Research Material and Reports
  The Research Material and Reports series illuminates Sunderland's intellectual process as he undertook projects large and small. Most of these files contain notes and collected material he carefully compiled for reference. Included are drafts, surveys and research material, many of which eventually became published reports, such as his study of the justice of the peace system and drafts prepared for the United States Supreme Court Advisory Committee on Rules for Civil Procedure.
  - Advisory Committee: United States Supreme Court Advisory Committee on Rules for Civil Procedure
    - 1935, 3 expandable folders (Box 1)
    - 1936 (Box 2)
    - 1937, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1939 (Box 2)
    - 1947 (Box 2)
    - 1948, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1949, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Appellate Courts Data Statutes 1929, undated (Box 2)
  - Appellate Procedure; American Bar Association Questionnaire "Letters In Reply," 1938 (Box 2)
  - Automobile Accident Study, Detroit Courts 1930 (Box 2)
  - Barnhart v. Barnhart, Collection of Authorities, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Brief, Flodin v. Guinup (Box 2)
  - Brief in Support of Special Appearance 1931 (Box 2)
  - Certiorari (Box 2)
  - Coca-Cola Case 1939 (Box 2)
  - Committees, Miscellaneous [missing] (Box 2)
  - Common Law, Forms of Action (Box 2)
  - Condemnation in Michigan 1929, undated (Box 3)
  - Condemnation Procedure 1928-1929 (Box 3)
  - Condemnation Rule 1948 (Box 3)
  - Continental Appellate Procedure (Box 3)
  - Courts: English, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Courts: German, Indian, French (Box 3)
  - Courts and Procedures (Box 3)
  - Court of Criminal Appeal: England (Box 3)
  - Court Rules of Michigan, Revised (Box 3)
  - Criminal Procedure (Box 3)
  - Declaratory Judgments 1926-1930 (Box 3)
  - Declaratory Judgment Cases (Box 3)
  - Declaratory Relief 1929 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Courts: Chief Justice Bill 1929 (Box 3)
  - Divisional Plan for Appellate Courts (Box 3)
  - Education, Legal (Box 3)
  - Ethics (Box 3)
  - Evidence, Error in regard to... (Box 3)
  - Family Law 1937, undated (Box 3)
  - Federal Rules, Notes (Box 3)
  - French Appellate Procedure (Box 3)
  - General Survey of Courts of Inferior Jurisdiction 1940 (Box 3)
  - Grand Jury (Box 3)
  - Illinois Practice Act, ca 1930-1934, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Judges (Box 3)
  - Judicial Administration
    - Sample Pleadings filed 1940 (Box 3)
    - Survey of the Administration of Justice, 1-4 (Box 3)
  - Judicial Council on Minor Court System: Suggestions for Legislation (Box 3)
  - Judicial System, Investigation, Volumes 1-4 1934, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Judicial System Investigation, Volumes 5-12 1934, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Justice of Peace Study
    - Data and Reports 1933, undated (Box 4)
    - Distribution 1942-1947 (Box 4)
    - Barry County 1942 (Box 4)
    - Highland Park and Detroit 1942 (Box 4)
    - Kalamazoo County 1942 (Box 4)
    - Monroe County 1942 (Box 4)
    - Ohio, Illinois, New York 1942, undated (Box 4)
    - Virginia, Maryland, District of Columbia 1940 (Box 4)
    - Statistics (Box 4)
    - Survey Results 1941, 5 expandable folders (Box 4)
    - Questionnaire on Justice of Peace (Box 4)
    - "Material Collected by Antiean and DeWitt on Justice of the Peace and Other Minor Courts" (Box 5)
  - Juries (Box 5)
  - Juvenile Courts (Box 5)
  - Legal Aid (Box 5)
  - Mentally Ill, Care of (Box 5)
  - Michigan Court Rules (Box 5)
  - Michigan Senate Bill No. 215 1941 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Statute of Limitations (notes) (3 expandable folders) (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Municipal Courts (Box 5)
  - Notes (subjects range from anti-trust law to verdicts), 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Notes (subjects range from anti-trust law to verdicts), 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Notes, Class
    - Judicial Administration, Volumes 1-4 (Box 6)
    - Limitations, Secondary Copy of Text, Volumes 1-2 (Box 6)
    - Limitations, Volumes 3-4 (Box 7)
    - Trial and Appellate Practice, Volumes 1, 3 (Box 7)
  - Opinions of Courts (Box 7)
  - Observations on Jury System [missing] (Box 7)
  - Organization, General (Box 7)
  - Patent Lawyers and Patent Law Associations (Box 7)
  - Practice Act, Illinois [missing] (Box 7)
  - Preserving Excluded Evidence (Box 7)
  - Pre-trial Conferences 1944, undated (Box 7)
  - Procedural Notes, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Proposals (Box 7)
  - Publications re: Legal Reform in England (Box 7)
  - Quotes and Humor (Box 7)
  - Respect for the Law (Box 7)
  - Redraft of Rules, Municipal Court of Chicago (Box 7)
  - Research Notebooks
    - Code Pleading (Box 7)
    - History of English Reform, 2 notebooks (Box 7)
    - Research in English Judicial System 1924 (Box 8)
    - Untitled (Box 8)
  - Review of Facts (Box 8)
  - Right of Petition (Box 8)
  - Rules: Civil Procedure 1936 (Box 8)
  - Rule Making Power (Box 8)
  - Rule Making Power, History of (Box 8)
  - Rules of Appellate Procedure (Box 8)
  - Sentences (Box 8)
  - State Projects circa 1929-1930 (Box 8)
  - Summary Judgments (Box 8)
  - "Sunderland's Cases on Common Law Pleading" (Box 8)
  - "Sunderland's Cases on Trial and Appellate Practice" (Box 8)
  - Survey of American Bar Association, 3 expandable folders (Box 8)
  - United Sates Code Lists, 1-50, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Voelker Seminar 1949 (Box 8)
  - Wickersham Reports (Box 8)
- Organizations and Committees
  The Organizations and Committees series effectively documents Sunderland's broad professional involvement throughout the state of Michigan and nationally. The series is arranged alphabetically, close to the order in which the files arrived at the Bentley Library (there are no files, however, with headings beyond "Montana Bar Association," an indication that some may never have arrived). A significant amount of material is held here on Sunderland's work with the United States Supreme Court, the American Bar Association and the Judicial Council. Conference materials, mainly from the 1930s, are also a part of the series.
  - Abstracts of Individual & Association Suggestions, Rule Numbers May 1936 (Box 9)
  - Advisory Committee: United States Supreme Court Advisory Committee on Federal Rules
    - General, 7 folders (Box 9)
    - Pepper, George W. (Drawings: cartoons on committee work) (Box 9)
  - Advisory Committee, U.S. Supreme Ct., Federal Rules, Working Notes, 1-5 1935, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Administrative Office of Michigan Courts (Box 9)
  - American Bar Association Activities
    - General, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Appellate Practice Committee 1938-1939, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Jurisprudence and Law Reform, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Survey of Legal Profession (Box 9)
  - American Judicature Society 1930-1932 (Box 9)
  - American Political Science Association, Administration of Justice 1947 (Box 9)
  - Chicago Bar Association (Box 9)
  - Children, Committee on Services for, in Michigan (Box 9)
  - Citizen's Committee for Better Government in Michigan (Box 9)
  - Committee on Civil Procedure, Michigan Bar Association 1944-1946 (Box 9)
  - Committee on Cooperation with the Bench and Bar 1933-1934 (Box 9)
  - Committee on Cooperation with American Law Institute 1932 (Box 9)
  - Committee on Curriculum of American Law Schools 1932 (Box 9)
  - Committee on Insane Persons, Commitment of (Box 9)
  - Committee of International Congress of Comparative Law (Box 9)
  - Committee on Public Utility Procedure 1932 (Box 9)
  - Conferences
    - Cincinnati, "Selection and Tenure of Judges," 1934 (Box 9)
    - National Conference of Judicial Councils 1930 (Box 9)
    - Minnesota Conference 1930 (Box 9)
    - Princeton Conference on Politics 1930 (Box 9)
    - Selection Tenure of Judges 1935 (Box 9)
  - Dunworkin Club, University of Michigan (Box 9)
  - Judicial Council 1929-1956 (Box 10)
    - General 1929-1948 scattered, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - General 1948-1956 scattered, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Appellate Court Organization 1932-1933 (Box 10)
    - Judicial Councils' Conferences 1928-1931 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence 1932-1951, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Proposed Court System (Box 10)
    - Reports 1953-1954 (Box 10)
  - Kingswood School, Cranbrook, Bloomfield Hills 1930-1933 (Box 10)
  - Lawyer's Club, 1927-33 (Box 10)
  - Legislation and Law Reform 1932-1933 (Box 10)
  - Louisiana State University 1938 (Box 10)
  - Michigan Committee on Legislation and Law Reform [missing] (Box 10)
  - Michigan Court Rules [missing] (Box 10)
  - Michigan State Bar Committee on Appellate Court (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Montana Bar Association 1939 (Box 10)
  - Style Committee, Memos 1937 (Box 10)
  - Style Committee, Rules, 1-94 1937 (Box 10)
- Correspondence
  There is extensive evidence related to Sunderland's activities in the Correspondence series, since it seems he faithfully saved a majority of documents that came in or went out of his office. The 4 linear feet of incoming and outgoing communication is, for the most part, arranged chronologically, with some years then foldered alphabetically. Approximately half a foot is arranged by subject. Additionally, there is correspondence to and from the Association of American Law Schools, material related to his work on discovery in the early 1930s, and documents to and from the Legal Research Institute.
  - By topic (Box 11)
    - Association of American Law Schools, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Dallas Legal Institute 1938 (Box 11)
    - Discovery, Legal Research Institute 1930-1931 (Box 11)
    - Dyer, Smith 1937-1938 (Box 11)
    - Federal Rules
      - 1935 (Box 11)
      - 1939 (Box 11)
      - 1948-1949 (Box 11)
    - J.J. Duggan Construction Company Proxy 1925-1941 (Box 11)
    - Law Reviews 1929-1936 (Box 11)
    - Legal Clients 1919-1945 (Box 11)
    - Legal Research Institute 1930-1945 (Box 11)
    - Related to Articles 1935-1937 (Box 11)
    - Supreme Court of Michigan 1929-1930 (Box 11)
  - By date
    - 1924-1928, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - 1928-1932, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - 1930-1932 A-Z, 8 folders (Box 11)
    - 1930-1932 Miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - 1932-1933 A-M, 10 folders (Box 12)
    - 1933-1939 A-R, 11 folders (Box 12)
    - 1933-1939 S-Z, 7 folders (Box 13)
    - 1934 A-Z, 21 folders (Box 13)
    - 1935 (Box 13)
    - 1936, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1936, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 14)
    - 1940-1952 A-Z, 13 folders (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous 1930s-1950s, 2 folders (Box 15)
- Law School, University of Michigan
  Less well documented is Sunderland's 43 year tenure as professor of law at the university. The series, Law School, University of Michigan, is slight, but contains notes for a handful of classes taught, material organized under the Legal Research Institute, some committee work and some correspondence. There are also three folders with memorabilia from Michigan Law School reunions.
  - Administrative Material 1939-1943 (Box 15)
  - Classes
    - Administrative Tribunals 1942-1943 (Box 15)
    - Common Law Pleading (Box 15)
    - Procedural Reform 1920-1921 (Box 15)
  - Committees, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Comparative Work (Box 15)
  - Cook Endowment (Box 15)
  - Correspondence 1922-1933, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Curriculum Changes (1931 ?) (Box 15)
  - Curriculum Committee 1932-1934 (Box 15)
  - Examination Questions, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Grading Systems (Box 15)
  - Law Review (Box 15)
  - Legal Research Institute
    - Federal Rules for Michigan and Misc. 1930-1931 (Box 15)
    - Intermediate Appellate Courts 1924-1929 (Box 15)
    - Legislative Reference Bureau 1931 (Box 15)
    - Local Government in Michigan 1931-1932 (Box 15)
    - Report 1930 (Box 15)
    - Ryland, George (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous Matters, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Outline of Procedures, Teaching Plan (Box 15)
  - Reorganization 1930 (Box 15)
  - Reports
    - Annual 1947, 1951 (Box 15)
    - Plans for Development of the Legal Research Institute (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - Research Committee 1941-1948 (Box 15)
  - Research Projects 1940-1947 (Box 16)
  - Reunions, Law School 1901-1902, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Yale Law School Appointment 1922-1923 (Box 16)
- Faculty Board in Control of Student Publications
  The Faculty Board in Control of Student Publications series is mainly comprised of correspondence related to Sunderland's more than 25 year association with the university's student publications -- the Michiganensian, Gargoyle, Perspectives and The Michigan Daily.
  - 1928-1930 (Box 16)
  - 1930-1931 (Box 16)
  - 1931-1932, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - 1934-1935 (Box 16)
  - 1938-1940, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Reports (Box 16)
- Speeches and Articles